<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?> 
<!-- was: <?xml version="1.0" ?> -->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="essayStyle.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Emily Tennyson’s Manuscript Music Books</rr-title></title>
                <author>Phyllis Weliver</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>composed by</resp>
                    <name>Bryan Haberberger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Center for Digital Humanities</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Saint Louis University</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Essay generated for the Sounding Tennyson project, creating an interactive 
                    exhibit for exploring resources and research around the poems and music of Tennyson.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016-01-19">19 Jan 2016</date> First build by BJH</item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                Four manuscript music books, conserved by the Lincolnshire County Council, contain no less than twenty-four piano/vocal settings of Alfred Tennyson’s poems, each in multiple drafts. The music is by the poet’s wife, Emily. Each setting is in Emily’s hand and identified at the top of the page with the amalgamated initials: “AET.” Examining the music and marginalia contained in the manuscript books reveals Emily’s creative life and also hints at the role played by the songs in the Tennysons’ relationship.
            </p>
            <figure>
                    <img src="media/mus_man_book.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 1. Emily Tennyson, manuscript music album, TRC/Music/5321. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
            </figure>
            <p>
                Before exploring the music books in some detail, it may be helpful to outline the sorts of compositions that they contain.  Most of the “AET” compositions are for solo voice and piano, but “The Sea Fairies,” “To sleep! to sleep” and “Hands all round” are choral, while “O Lark!” appears in two versions, for solo voice and for two voices. One of these manuscript books, catalogued as 5321, additionally contains standard German, Italian and English drawing-room repertoire. While all four music books functioned as revision and pre-publication tools for Emily’s musical settings and Tennyson’s poems, this last album more comprehensively memorializes the Tennysons’ social and family life.
            <p>
               The musical album – a hybrid of popular drawing-room repertoire interleaved with Emily Tennyson’s compositions – is the longest and visually the most striking of the manuscript music books. It is bound in red half-calf over board with “MS MUSIC” in gold tooling on the spine. (Fig. 1.) The AET poems in this volume include first drafts of the settings, many of which are followed later in the album with second, third and even fourth drafts. As for the selections composed by other people, they are also in Emily’s hand. Victorian ladies typically played from published music (usually sheet music) or hand-copied songs and piano pieces. Emily Tennyson did own published music, at least some of which is under the custodianship of the <rr-footnote>Lincolnshire County Council,</rr-footnote>  but copying out favorite repertoire saved money. The time-consuming process also helped women to become familiar with compositional techniques. In considering the music books of Jane Austen and her family, Kathryn L. Libin puts it thus:
               <rr-line-indent>
                Music copying represents a union of discipline and devotion; it demonstrates that the copyist has appropriated the music, and absorbed it within her self. When we have taken the trouble to commit a piece of music painstakingly, note by note, to memory, it is no accident that we say we have “learned it by <i>heart</i>.” We might likewise say that in copying out music, we have learned it by hand; and then, by gathering it all together into a bound volume, created a meaningful memoir of our encounter. One might consider such an album to be a kind of musical commonplace <rr-footnote>book</rr-footnote> 
               </rr-line-indent>
               Music might also be copied into a single “melodious volume” or “portfolio” that could be produced when a lady was invited to play after London dinners and during country house <rr-footnote>visits.</rr-footnote> 

            </p>
            <p>
                It is unclear how the music in Emily’s album functioned, however, because of its history as a book. A conservator has identified the binding as dating from between the 1920s to late 1950s, which may mean that that the Tennysons’ only surviving son, Hallam, organized it before his death in <rr-footnote>1928.</rr-footnote>  Regardless, someone in the twentieth century bound together miscellaneous music sheets, many of them probably loose since the pages have various borders. The order of the individual pieces does not necessarily show chronology, although some sequencing is implied. More of the standard drawing room music appears first. Turning the pages, we exponentially find Emily’s settings of Alfred’s poems from 1832 to 1892, interleaved with contemporaneous music by other composers, somewhat like the assembly of a photo album or scrapbook from scattered pictures of earlier times. In such books, items are often placed in approximate order. Of course, Emily may have organized the contents herself if the current binding replaces some sort of folder or <rr-footnote>box.</rr-footnote>  In that case, the collected music would have functioned as Emily’s favorite drawing-room selections, her compositions, and a group of family memories. The nostalgic value of the music is shown through the album’s inclusion of mementos from her sons’ youth, including Emily’s composition, “Hallam and Lionel’s Lullaby” (surely sung to the children), and a young Hallam’s attempt to take musical dictation.
            </p>
            <p>
                From the type of music included in the album, we can surmise that Emily played most of drawing-room repertoire to Alfred, probably during courtship as well as marriage. Aside from Emily’s compositions, the album contains typical genre choices for nineteenth-century music collections: waltzes, opera excerpts and airs by Romantic composers such as Mrs. Robert Arkwright <rr-footnote>(née Fanny Kemble).</rr-footnote>  Tennyson, who played the flute, loved to listen to just this sort of music: “the simple style of Mozart, and […] our own national airs and ballads,” as Hallam noted in the <i>Memoir</i> of his <rr-footnote>father.</rr-footnote>  Similarly, Emily set in simple style Tennyson’s patriotic poems (e.g., “Riflemen form!” “Britons, Guard your own,” “I go to die for Scotland” from <i>The Foresters</i>), love songs (“Love that hath us in the net” and “Look thro’ mine eyes with thine” from <i>The Miller’s Daughter</i>), and poetry suitable for children (“Sweet and Low,” “Airy Fairy Lillian,” “The Sea Fairies,” “Minnie and Winnie,” and “To sleep! To sleep!” from <i>The Foresters</i>). As for “complicated music,” Edward FitzGerald, translator of <i>The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám</i> (1859), attests that Tennyson only enjoyed that “suggesting echoes of winds and <rr-footnote>waves.”</rr-footnote>  Although it is not complicated, Emily’s music for “Sweet and Low” seems to reflect this sensibility.
            </p>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/mus_man_1.jpg" style="width:32%;" />
                    <img src="media/mus_man_2.jpg" style="width:32%;" />
                    <img src="media/mus_man_3.jpg" style="width:32%;" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 2. Emily Tennyson, manuscript music books (red, pink and green covers), TRC/Music/5312/3, TRC/Music/5312/1, TRC/Music/5312/2. These items are reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
            <p>
                The album contains many of the earliest versions of the AET songs which were then revised in the three manuscript music books. (Fig. 2.) Revisions to the album along with some new compositions are located in a manuscript music book with commercially-ruled 12-stave pages, bound in red calf over board with elegant gold tooled decoration along the sides and corners (catalogue 5312/3). Some settings are sketched out for the first time here, such as “Dead Mountain Flower” and the Count’s Song from <i>The Falcon</i> (1879). In this red book, there are also many additional copies (from second to fourth revisions) of AET compositions, first found either in this red book (5312/3) or in the album (5321). A pink commercial manuscript music book contains more first drafts of AET compositions (5312/1). These pieces set the texts of some of Tennyson’s late poems (“God and the Universe,” “The Silent Voices,” and songs from <i>The Foresters</i>). Lastly, a green manuscript music book contains final, clean versions of many AET works that were first drafted and revised in the other books (5312/2). Hallam made a memo to this effect on the draft of “Break, Break, Break” in the red book. He wrote, “Copied on green book”:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/emilys_hand.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 3. Hallam Tennyson’s hand, “Copied in green book” on Emily Tennyson, “Break, Break, Break,” music manuscript book (pink cover), TRC/Music/5312/1, f11r. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote> </figcaption>
                </figure>
                As we can see, someone crossed out the page, too, and changed the Roman numeral at the top. Perhaps it was Hallam. Since these markings are all in pencil, did he reorder, lightly score through and comment during the same sitting?
            </p>

            <p>
                Taken together, the manuscript music books provide detailed information about Emily’s creative response to Tennyson’s poems. We know that Emily offered feedback on Alfred’s written and <rr-footnote>recited drafts,</rr-footnote>  too, but her dedication to and collaboration with this compositional process is perhaps most striking in how scrupulously she worked through and copied out multiple drafts of scored notation. In at least one case, her music seems to have influenced his poetic choices. Emily made sure to note the fact on the first draft of “Sweet and Low,” from <i>The Princess</i>: “Written to the songs before this was published”:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/emilys_hand_2.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 4. Emily Tennyson’s hand, “Written to the songs before this was published,” note on Emily Tennyson, “Sweet and Low,” manuscript music album, TRC/Music/5321, f 149v. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                Moreover, the laureate’s drafting process sometimes juxtaposed spoken performance with listening to relevant folk music. When Tennyson was writing “Enid” for the <cite>Idylls of the King</cite>, a poem in which the eponymous character’s singing inspires her future husband to marry her, Emily reported that her husband performed the work in progress over a six-month period, during which time she played relevant <rr-footnote>music.</rr-footnote>  “We make out a little of ‘Enid’ in Welsh & in the evening I play some Welsh airs & A. [Alfred] reads as much of his ‘Enid’ as is sufficiently finished”, Emily wrote in her <rr-footnote>journal.</rr-footnote>  Welsh language and music thus both influence the composition of “Enid.” As the example of “Break, Break, Break” shows, even after a poem was published and seemingly finished, the Tennysons returned to it and changed how it was articulated. 

            </p>

            <p>
                Clearly, Emily’s musicality contributed to Alfred’s compositional process, but how do we determine the extent of their collaboration? Other essays on the <i>Sounding Tennyson</i> site offer case-by-case insights by exploring individual AET songs in detail. We can also study textual annotations in the manuscript music books which establish Emily Tennyson’s legacy and preserve intentionality. Inside the green cover, Hallam emphasized his mother’s artistic ownership: “The Original Melodies [& accompaniments] by Emily Lady Tennyson”:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig9.png" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 5. Hallam Tennyson’s hand, except for “accompaniment” which is unknown, in Emily Tennyson, music manuscript book (green cover), TRC/Music/5312/2, inside cover. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                As the book of final drafts, maybe this volume was the obvious place to document Emily’s original intent (as opposed to the changes introduced by arrangers of the music)? In contrast, glosses in the other books register the relationship of Emily’s music to Tennyson’s recitations:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig4.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 6. Unknown hand, despite Hallam’s “signature,” in Emily Tennyson, manuscript music album, TRC/Music/5321, f 1. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig11.png" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 7. Hallam Tennyson’s hand, in Emily Tennyson, manuscript music book (pink cover), TRC/Music/5312/1, inside cover. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig12.png" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 8. Hallam Tennyson’s hand, in Emily Tennyson, manuscript music book (red cover), TRC/Music/5312/3, f 1. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                Perhaps the green book, as a final record of Emily’s compositional intentions, qualified it in Hallam’s eyes for a different representation of his mother’s achievements from the earlier drafts. Hallam thus describes the drafting process as bilateral, but the finished music as his mother’s.
            </p>

            <p>
                Attribution is not quite that easy, however. One of the most interesting features of the book is the mingled “AET” initials in the headers of Emily’s settings of Alfred’s poems. The initials are more complicated than a simple label or stamp, for Emily’s hand forms the “ET,” while the “A” appears to have been added later. In certain songs, for example, “ET” is in ink while “A” is in <rr-footnote>pencil:</rr-footnote> 
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/emilys_hand_3.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 9. Emily Tennyson, “Britons Rise,” music manuscript album, TRC/Music/5321, f 55. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/emilys_hand_4.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 10. Emily Tennyson, “A Call to Arms,” music manuscript album, TRC/Music/5321, f 58. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/emilys_hand_5.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 11. Emily Tennyson, “Hands all round,” music manuscript album, TRC/Music/5321, f 59. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                On at least one page, the “A” looks like Alfred’s <rr-footnote>writing:</rr-footnote>   
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/emilys_hand_6.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 12. Emily Tennyson, “Riflemen Form,” music manuscript album, TRC/Music/5321, f 52. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                In other words, Emily initialed her compositions to identify the music as her own and thus follows the standard practice of categorizing songs by composer. Then another person (or people) later added Alfred’s initial. The “A” (re)presents Emily’s vocal melodies and piano accompaniment as a mixture of Alfred and Emily Tennyson; unusually, it gives equal credit to lyricist and composer. In those instances when Alfred added his own initial to the “AET,” it was a form of signature and an intimate act of intermingling identity, but did Emily request the added initial?
            </p>

            <p>
               Regardless of who added the “A,” the combined “AET” marks a true collaboration in the songs. In a sense, the initials also convey something about the nature of the music and poetry in the Tennysons’ marriage. Emily, for one, aspired to “make one music” with her husband, as she put it during the 1848 courtship, by which she meant moving in similar “worlds of religious <rr-footnote>thought”.</rr-footnote>  Taking this “one music” statement literally, the songs contribute to and reflect Alfred and Emily Tennyson (the couple), as much as the people (“AET”) make the songs.
            </p>
    
                <rr-bib>
                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>This</rr-footnote> set of music is catalogued as Emily Tennyson’s. Only the last item has a note specifically identifying it as such. [Collection of Music: Songs, etc. by various composers], John Clarke and others [undated], TRC/ET/3314; [Collection of music for the piano], Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart and others [undated], TRC/ET/3603; <i>The Musical Gem: A Souvenir for 1832</i>, eds Nicolas Mori and W. Ball (Mori and Lavenu: 1832), TRC/ET/3358; <i>A Selection of the songs of Lady Dufferin (Countess of Gifford) set to music</i>, ed. by her son the Marquess of Dufferin (Murray: 1895), TRC/ET/3592.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Kathryn</rr-footnote> L. Libin, “Daily Practice, Musical Accomplishment, and the Example of Jane Austen,” <i>Jane Austen and the Arts: Elegance, Propriety, and Harmony</i>, eds Natasha Duquette and Elisabeth Lenckos (Bethlehem: Lehigh University Press, 2014) 10. Original emphasis. </rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>E.F.</rr-footnote> Benson, <i>As We Were: A Victorian Peep-Show</i> (London: Longmans, Green, 1930) 19.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>It</rr-footnote> is unclear how much the materials were cared for between Hallam’s death and 1963, when the stored items were unpacked at the Tennyson Research Centre under Charles Tennyson’s oversight (grandson to the poet). Grace Timmins, emails to author, 24 and 28 October 2014.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>It</rr-footnote> is unlikely that there was a prior, single binding. Since the music spans Emily’s adult life, it could only have been bound in the 1890s. Such a binding would not have needed replacing in the twentieth century.</rr-bib-entry>
 
                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>For</rr-footnote> discussions of music albums, see Michelle Meinhart, “Mourning and Memorial: Memory and Private Mourning in an English Country House during the First World War: Lady Alda Hoare’s Musical Shrine to a Lost Son,” <i>Journal of Musicological Research</i> 33 (2014): 39-95; Jeanice Brooks, “Musical Monuments for the Country House: Music, Collection, and Display at Tatton Park,” <i>Music & Letters</i> 91.4 (2010): 513-35.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Hallam</rr-footnote> Tennyson, <i>Alfred Lord Tennyson: A Memoir by his Son</i>, 2 vols (1897; New York: Macmillan, 1898) 1: 77.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Ibid.</rr-footnote></rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Grace</rr-footnote> Timmins, email to author, 2 February 2016.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Emily</rr-footnote> Tennyson, 8 February 1859, 21 October 1861, 13 January and 23 February 1862, <i>The Farringford Journal of Emily Tennyson, 1853-1864</i>, eds Richard J. Hutchings and Brian Hinton (Newport: Isle of Wight County Press, 1986) 79-80, 102, 104, 105.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Emily</rr-footnote> Tennyson first read “Enid” to herself on 4 April 1856 and two months later the poet began to read drafts aloud to his wife. He also recited to John Simeon during his visit on 15 December. Emily Tennyson, 4 April, 4 June, 15 June, 29 September, 13/14 October, 18 October, 6 November, 11 November, 17 November, 15 December 1856, <i>Emily Tennyson’s Journal</i>, ed. James O. Hoge (Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1981) 64, 72, 73, 75, 76, 77, 78, 80. Cited by Bushell, <i>Text as Process</i>, 122.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Emily</rr-footnote> Tennyson, 29 September 1856, <i>Emily Tennyson’s Journal</i>, 75.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Grace</rr-footnote> Timmins, email to author, 2/8/16.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Grace</rr-footnote> Timmins, email to author, 2/8/16.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Christopher</rr-footnote> Ricks, <i>Tennyson</i>, (1972), 2nd ed (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1989) 196.</rr-bib-entry>
                </rr-bib>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
