<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="essayStyle.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>To Break or not to Break? Emily Tennyson’s scansion of ‘Break, break, break’</title>
                <author>Phyllis Weliver</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>composed by</resp>
                    <name>Patrick Cuba</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Center for Digital Humanities</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Saint Louis University</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Essay generated for the Sounding Tennyson project, creating an interactive 
                    exhibit for exploring resources and research around the poems and music of Tennyson.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016-01-19">19 Jan 2016</date> First build by PMC</item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <rr-title type="poem">Break, break, break</rr-title> is the only poem that Emily Tennyson set to music and that her husband, Alfred Tennyson, later recorded on a phonograph. The poet laureate may have deemed it especially worthy of preservation because during his lifetime <rr-title type="poem">Break, break, break</rr-title> had already attracted myriad scansions by poetic theorists and <rr-footnote>composers.</rr-footnote>  Indeed, much critical attention still focuses on how to say the first line, which is the same as the title: "Break, break, <rr-footnote>break."</rr-footnote>
            </p>
            <p>
                How do we read this line? Do we observe the commas in “Break, break, break,” savoring each pause in order to approximate the length of the poem’s other lines? The poem’s line lengths vary from seven to eleven beats in addition to the famous first line, which repeats at the beginning of the last stanza (line 13). Or do we roll through the commas as Tennyson frequently does in the extant phonograph recitations, making “Break, break, break” a straightforward three beats? Because the words are exactly repeated in line 13, is this iteration scanned the same as line 1? What did Tennyson himself choose to do?
            </p>
            <p>
                Many people heard Tennyson recite the poem, and many others said it aloud to the poet and his family. Perhaps their punctuation when they wrote down the title of the poem offers a clue to how the first line was typically said in Victorian Britain. Every time that Emily Tennyson mentions the poem in her diary, she leaves out the commas. This happens when she noted her husband’s recitation of “Break Break” in 1857 and a child’s in 1859, as well as when Elizabeth Jane, Lady Charlemont and wife of James Molyneux, 3rd earl of Charlemont, read “Break break break” to the poet in 1871:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig1.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 1. Emily Tennyson, 3 Nov 1857, Diary, vol. 1, f 126, TRC/M50. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote> </figcaption>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig2.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 2. Emily Tennyson, 1 July 1859, Diary, vol. 1, f 171, TRC/M50. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote> </figcaption>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig3.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 3. Emily Tennyson, 30 June 1871, Diary, vol. 2, f 180, TRC/M50. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote></figcaption>
                </figure>
                This, the only extant copy of the diary, was re-written by Emily for her son Hallam’s use in preparing Tennyson’s memoir. The diarist may have consistently omitted the commas because she was writing hurriedly. However, Mary Gladstone similarly left out the commas when noting the poem in her diary. The lack of punctuation in then-contemporary life writing may possibly reveal how people of various ages and walks of life said (and heard) the poem or it may also indicate different grammar norms.
            </p>
            <p>
                Emily’s piano/vocal scores give us a more accurate idea of her husband’s recitations, as a note makes clear. In the fly-leaf of one of his mother’s four music manuscript books, someone wrote at Hallam’s bequest (although “signed” Hallam, the handwriting is not his) :
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig4.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 4. MS music book settings by Emily Tennyson of Alfred Tennyson’s poems, TRC/Music/5321, f 1. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote></figcaption>
                </figure>
                Examining Emily Tennyson’s musical setting of “Break, break, break” reveals that she heard the first line of poem as in the manuscript:
                 <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig5.png" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 5. Alfred Tennyson, "Break, break, break,” manuscript copy, HM 19490. This item is reproduced by permission of The Huntington Library, San Marino, California. <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote></figcaption>
                </figure>
                Unlike the published version, Tennyson’s draft does not include a comma after the third “break.” Emily’s musical treatment similarly breaks after the first two words and then runs over the line break. With fermatas and rests on the first two “breaks,” the music melodramatically emphasizes each of the first two words, before continuing onto the ideas of the rest of the stanza: the speaker’s heartbreak equated to, or heard in, the breaking surf.
            </p>
            <p>
                Significantly, Emily set “Break, break, break” differently in line 13. The commas are no longer strongly marked by rests. Of course, the concluding “k” in “break” still introduces some separation between each of the three stressed words, but the overall effect is to carry on. The other musical settings of the poem on this website treat both lines the same: the composition by Georg Henschel and the arrangement of Emily’s music by Polish pianist, Natalie Janotha (she additionally changes line 1 to omit the rests).
            </p>
            <p>
                The effect of Emily’s different sonorous choices lines 1 and 13 affects the meaning of the poem. The strong pauses in line 1 emphasize the poet’s breaking heart and voice (no voice fills in the silence), which corresponds to the desolate landscape (“cold gray”).  The reiteration of “Break, break, break” (line 13) occurs after a stanza that juxtaposes a divine afterlife (“stately ships / […] haven under the hill”) with the speaker’s desire for his dead friend’s “touch” and “voice”. The friend is no longer physically present, but the landscape is. The breaking surf is now characterized simply as the crag’s “foot” (another bodily reference). With no rests between the “breaks,” the sound of the sea now seems emphasized over the breaking of the heart; the words run into each other like the indistinct roar of the sea far below, rather than the painfully differentiated beats of the poet’s grief-stricken heart. It is as if the speaker is moving on with his life. That said, the breaking heart is residually echoed or implied in line 13 because of the exact repetition of the poem’s opening words. Then the final two lines, beginning with “But”, present a qualified thought. The speaker recognizes that despite his healing heart, the friend will never again be embodied in the flesh, as well as spiritually present. This spiritual presence is musically communicated because divine “stately ships” (line 9) sounds similar to “tender grace” (line 15). Linking the words through their musical settings gives religious meaning to “tender grace”; we hear this definitively in Emily Tennyson’s musical choices. Reading the poem on the page does not necessarily reveal that “tender grace” is Christian grace.
            </p>
            <p>
                The sonorous effect of reading to or against the commas in “Break, break, break” thus emerges not only in critical commentary, but also in Emily’s music – the impression of Tennyson’s recitation. Rather than making an either/or choice (to break or not), however, the Tennysons’ articulation(s) inscribed the rich variety of each possibility into the poem. Emily’s musical setting reveals how the emotional extremes of the poem’s first line (melodramatic breaks at each comma) progress to resignation as the speaker continues to mourn, but is no longer defined by harrowing pain. Rather than querying whether “to break or not to break,” to borrow Hamlet’s famous line, Alfred and Emily Tennyson chose both; they break, and then they do not break. Our experience of the poem echoes this choice: the heart breaks (pauses), while yet we carry on.
            </p>

            <rr-bib>

                <rr-bib-entry>
                    <rr-footnote>See</rr-footnote> Yopie Prins, “‘Break, Break, Break’ into Song,” <i>Meter Matters: Verse Cultures of the Long Nineteenth Century</i>, ed. Jason David Hall (Athens: Ohio University Press, 2011) 110, 121.
                </rr-bib-entry>

                <rr-bib-entry>
                    <rr-footnote>For</rr-footnote> example, Derek Attridge, “Beat,” <i>The Oxford Handbook of Victorian Verse</i>, ed. Matthew Bevis (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013) 36–7.
                </rr-bib-entry>

                <rr-bib-entry>
                    <rr-footnote>“We</rr-footnote> drive with Mrs Cameron to see the Carlyles. Mr Carlyle admits us tho’ against rule to admit guests in the morning. We return thro’ Wimbledon Park. Mr Henry Taylor, Mr Lear, Williams, Mr Rossetti, Mr Holman Hunt, Mr Woolner dine. Lady Charlotte & her party come in the evening. All pleased with Mr Lear’s singing. A [Alfred] reads the Morte d’Arthur & Break break after he has sent me to bed. Most hospitably most kindly have we been received by our friends in their houses. We are grateful for all the enjoyment we have had.” Emily Tennyson, 3 November 1857, Diary, vol 1, f 126. TRC/M50, Lincolnshire County Council, UK.
                </rr-bib-entry>

                <rr-bib-entry>  
                    <rr-footnote>“Mrs</rr-footnote> Cameron goes. Frederic crosses with her. Meanwhile Hallam & I call on Captain & Mrs. Hamond in their new house. Very charming it is. A [Alfred] will delight in the lawn. Their little Carry says, Break break to me in such a touching sweet voice. While the Grants & Mr. Ferrier are dining with us there is a fearful thunder storm, hailstones as big as Walnuts, the kitchen two or three inches deep in water which comes into nearly every bedroom. Merwood pierces holes in the bathroom ceiling to let the water off & so preserve the ceiling. [paragraph break] Just before the storm begins Mrs Cameron’s Ellen arrives to our astonishment. She is sent to ask for the manuscript of Guinevere. A [Alfred] does not care about his manuscripts. He gives them to anyone who asks. To me they are more precious than words can say. Every page almost a memory. He is so good as to say that if I do not like to part from it and he has promised it, he will copy it out rather than that I should have to part from it.” Emily Tennyson, 1 July 1859, Diary, vol 1, f 171, TRC/M50, Lincolnshire County Council, UK.
                </rr-bib-entry>

                <rr-bib-entry>
                    <rr-footnote>“Mrs</rr-footnote> Greville, Lady Charlemont, Mr Locker, & Admiral Englefield come to luncheon. A [Alfred] & Hallam have called on Mrs Hodgson in the morning & asked her to meet Mrs Greville in the afternoon. She & her sister Miss Forsyth come. A [Alfred] reads Boadicea & part of Maud to them & Lady Charlemont recites or rather acts the Sisters after A [Alfred] has at her request read it & then she reads Break break break. [space] All have tea & go, except Mr Locker, just as Mr & Mrs Farrar arrive.” Emily Tennyson, 30 June 1871, Diary, vol 2, f 180, TRC/M50. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.
                </rr-bib-entry>

                <rr-bib-entry>
                    <rr-footnote>Grace</rr-footnote> Timmins, email to author, 2 February 2016.
                </rr-bib-entry>

                <rr-bib-entry>
                    <rr-footnote>My</rr-footnote> Mother’s settings of my Fathers’ Poems were made mostly after she had first heard them read by him; and give the impression of my Fathers’ reading. Therefore, Stanford advised me to keep them, and make a note of the fact. Hallam T.” TRC/Music/5321, f 1. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.
                </rr-bib-entry>

            </rr-bib>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>