<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="essayStyle.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Emily Tennyson's Music Manuscript Books</title>
                <author>Phyllis Weliver</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>composed by</resp>
                    <name>Bryan Haberberger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Center for Digital Humanities</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Saint Louis University</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Essay generated for the Sounding Tennyson project, creating an interactive 
                    exhibit for exploring resources and research around the poems and music of Tennyson.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016-01-19">19 Jan 2016</date> First build by BJH</item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <rr-float-l-fig>
                    <figure>
                        <img src="media/mus_man_book.jpg"/>
                        <figcaption>Fig. 6.  Manuscript music album by Emily Lady Tennyson of Alfred Lord Tennyson's poems, Catalogue No.5321, Tennyson Research Center.  Lincolnshire county council (hereafter TRC).</figcaption>
                    </figure>
                </rr-float-l-fig>
                Emily Tennyson’s four music manuscript books, preserved at the Tennyson Research Centre, contain multiple drafts of twenty-four piano/vocal scores with music by herself and words by her husband, Alfred Tennyson. Each setting is in Emily’s hand and identified at the top of the page with the amalgamated initials: “AET.” Most are for solo voice and piano, but “The Sea Fairies,” “To sleep! to sleep” and “Hands all round” are choral, while “O Lark!” appears in two versions, for solo voice and for two voices. One of these books additionally contains standard German, Italian and English drawing-room repertoire. While all four music books functioned as revision and pre-publication tools for Emily’s settings and Tennyson’s poems, this last album more fully memorializes the Tennysons’ social life because it contains music that pleased the pianist and her listeners.
            </p>
            <p>
                This musical album – a hybrid of popular drawing-room repertoire interleaved with Emily Tennyson’s compositions, arrangements and settings of Tennyson’s poems – is visually the most striking of the music books. It is bound in red half-calf over board with “MS MUSIC” in gold tooling on the spine (5321). (Fig. 6.) The AET poems in this album include first drafts of settings, many of which are followed later in the album with second, third and even fourth drafts. The non-Tennyson settings are also in Emily’s hand. Victorian ladies frequently played from published sheet music or their own hand-copied songs and piano pieces. Copying out favorite repertoire meant that women saved money and also became familiar with compositional techniques through the painstaking process. If Emily Tennyson owned published music, it has not been retained in her library, which is otherwise preserved at the Tennyson Research Centre.
            </p>
            <p>
                Frequently, hand-copied music such as this was bound as an elegant and portable book that could easily be produced when a lady was asked to play after London dinners and during country house visits. However, Emily’s ill health perhaps explains why this music album did not function thus (a hostess would not have requested Emily to play). Rather, a conservator has identified the binding of the album as dating from between the 1920s to late 1950s, which may mean that that her only surviving son, Hallam Tennyson, organized it before his death in 1928.  Regardless, someone in the twentieth century bound together miscellaneous music sheets, many of them probably loose since the pages have various borders. The order of the individual pieces does not necessarily show chronology, although some chronology is implied. More of the standard drawing room music appears first. Then, as we continue to turn the album’s pages, we find exponentially more of Emily’s settings of Tennyson’s poems from 1832 to 1892, interleaved with contemporaneous music by other composers, somewhat like the assembly of a photo album from scattered pictures of earlier times. In that case, items are often placed in approximate order. 
            </p>
            <p>
                Along with Emily’s compositions, the album contains typical genre choices for nineteenth-century music collections: waltzes, opera excerpts and drawing-room airs by Romantic composers such as Mrs. Robert Arkwright (née Fanny Kemble).  Tennyson, who played the flute, loved to listen to just this sort of music: “the simple style of Mozart, and […] our own national airs and ballads,” as his son Hallam noted in Tennyson’s Memoir.  Similarly, Emily set in simple style Tennyson’s patriotic poems (e.g., “Riflemen form!” “Britons, Guard your own,” “I go to die for Scotland” from The Foresters), love songs (“Love that hath us in the net” and “Look thro’ mine eyes with thine” from The Miller’s Daughter), and poetry suitable for children (“Sweet and Low,” “Airy Fairy Lillian,” “The Sea Fairies,” “Minnie and Winnie,” and “To sleep! To sleep!” from The Foresters). As for “complicated music,” Edward FitzGerald, translator of The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám (1859), attested that Tennyson only enjoyed that “suggesting echoes of winds and waves.”  Emily’s composition for “Sweet and Low” seems to reflect this sensibility.
            </p>
            <p>
                <rr-inline-fig>
                    <img src="media/mus_man_1.jpg"/>
                    <figcaption>Fig. 7. Music manuscript books (Red, Pink, Green)</figcaption>
                </rr-inline-fig>
                <rr-inline-fig>
                    <img src="media/mus_man_2.jpg"/>
                </rr-inline-fig>
                <rr-inline-fig>
                    <img src="media/mus_man_3.jpg"/>
                </rr-inline-fig>
            </p>
            <p>
                The album contains many of the earliest drafts of the AET songs which were then revised in the three music manuscript books (Fig. 7). Revisions to the album along with some new compositions are found in a music manuscript book with commercially-ruled 12-stave pages, bound in red calf over board with elegant gold tooled decoration along the sides and corners (5312/3). Some settings are found for the first time here, such as “Dead Mountain Flower” and the Count’s Song from The Falcon (1879). In this red book, there are also many additional drafts (from second to fourth revisions) of AET compositions, first found either in this red book (5312/3) or in the album (5321). A pink commercial music manuscript book contains more first drafts of AET compositions (5312/1). These compositions set the texts of some of Tennyson’s late poems (“God and the Universe,” “The Silent Voices,” and songs from The Foresters). Lastly, a green music manuscript book contains final, clean versions of many AET songs that were first drafted and revised in the other books (5312/2). Hallam made a note to this effect on the copy of “Break, break, break” in the red book, “copied on green book,” and then crossed out the page:
            </p>
            <p>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig8.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 8. 5312/1, f11r. Hallam Tennyson’s writing, pencil note, ‘Copied in green book’. </figcaption>
                </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
                In the green book, Hallam emphasized his mother’s artistic ownership, while in other books we find notes about the relationship of the music to Tennyson’s recitations. Thus Hallam noted inside the front cover of the green book, “The Original Melodies [& accompaniments] by Emily Lady Tennyson”:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig9.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 9. Hallam Tennyson’s hand, except for ‘accompaniment’ which is unknown. 5312/2. TRC.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                This formulation is slightly different from the notes inside the other books, which all refer to the relation between the music and Tennyson’s recitations:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig10.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 10. Unknown hand. MS music book settings by Emily Lady Tennyson of Alfred Lord Tennyson’s poems, Catalogue No. 5321, f 1. TRC.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig11.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 11. Hallam Tennyson’s hand, 5312/1. TRC.</figcaption>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/fig12.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>Figure 12. Hallam Tennyson’s hand, 5312/1. TRC.</figcaption>
                </figure>

                Did Hallam conceive of his mother’s vocal melodies and piano accompaniment as entirely a record of his father’s recitations, as her own contribution, or a mixture of Alfred and Emily Tennyson (thus the amalgamated “AET” at the top of each page)? Perhaps in the green book, Hallam simply wished to record original intent as opposed to the changes that Janotha later introduced into her arrangements. Regardless, Emily was involved in creative response to Tennyson’s poetry through painstaking and time-consuming multiple music drafts. Through publication, she intended that this music would resound in parlors around Britain.  
            </p>

            <p>
                <rr-bib>
                    16  In fact, Alfred Tennyson supplied the first stanza to The Song of the Alma River. Editorial note, The Letters of Alfred Lord Tennyson, Vol II: 1851:1870, eds Cecil Y. Lang and Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. (Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 1987) 2: 374 n1.

                    17  I changed melodies!!??
                    Lady Tennyson changed accompaniment!?
                    Wood changed both -
                    + I changed at last
                    “all in all”
                    leaving all the beautiful
                    + the only true, as you 
                          liked it!! –

                    18   Dear Mrs. Tennyson,
                    The song is published in two keys, E + F. The latter also because Santley can’t sing it in so low a key – The lie of the notes is (as I think I told you at the time) too low for the ordinary voice to bring out with any effect at all – that is if you wish the same voice to sing the high notes as well. I am afraid that even in the higher key the song won’t be so effective when sung as it looks upon paper or sounds on the piano; but this we must risk. I left it to Santley (as the best judge of what his own voice can do) to fix the key - + he chose F as I expected. The song will appear in the original key also I hope that you will not mind. […]


                   19 Janotha to Emily Tennyson, 2 January 1890, Catalogue 3813; 16 March 1891, Catalogue 6866; Tennyson Research Centre.

                   20 Janotha to Charles Flower, 21 February 1891, OCLC Number 471921271, Folger Library; Natalie Janotha to Mary Gladstone, 18 and 20 September 1891, BL Add MS 46245, ff 148, 151.

                   21 Mdlle. Janotha’s Concert, The Musical Times (1 April 1891) 217.

                   22  Press clippings from the Standard, Truth and The Musical Standard, Catalogue 6877. Tennyson Research Centre, Lincolnshire County Council.
                      Sweet precious composer!
                    On the 26th -
                    Miss Breman sings
                    “Look through mine eyes”
                    “in [sic]Love if Love”
                    --
                    Miss Elliot
                    “Airy Fairy Lilian” (2nd arrangement)
                    --
                    Mr. Ley
                    “to [sic] sleep
                    “Home they brought him
                    “Lady let the rolling
                    + 
                    23 Rifleman.
                    They do adore these songs + I also
                    N. –


                </rr-bib>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>