<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="essayStyle.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Performing and Publishing Emily Tennyson’s Music</title>
                <author>Phyllis Weliver</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>composed by</resp>
                    <name>Bryan Haberberger</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Center for Digital Humanities</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Saint Louis University</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available on a non-commercial basis.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2016">2016</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Essay generated for the Sounding Tennyson project, creating an interactive 
                    exhibit for exploring resources and research around the poems and music of Tennyson.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <list>
                <item>
                    <date when="2016-01-19">19 Jan 2016</date> First build by BJH</item>
            </list>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                Over the course of almost thirty years, Emily Tennyson published sheet music for solo voice and piano. Although forgotten until now, in late Victorian Britain these musical settings of Alfred Tennyson’s poems were well received in parlors and the concert hall. Inside a manuscript music album, Hallam Tennyson clearly linked his parents’ creative efforts: “My Mother’s settings of my Fathers’ Poems were made mostly after she had first heard them read by him; and give the impression of my Fathers’ <rr-footnote>reading.”</rr-footnote>  The “impression” of Tennyson’s recitations, captured by his wife’s vocal lines, thus reached a wide audience through musical performance and publication. Natalie Janotha, a Polish pianist who had studied with Clara Schumann, played an especially vital role in facilitating these transmissions of Tennyson’s readings, for she arranged and promoted nine of Emily’s sixteen published songs.
            </p>

            <p>
                Before concentrating on Janotha’s notable contributions, I wish to contextualize Emily’s musical settings. To begin with, a then-contemporary response to Tennyson’s reading voice reveals that Emily made a critical, interpretative choice in how she set the poems. In August 1871, the Tennysons visited novelist George Eliot and her partner, George Henry Lewes. Emily reported to her eldest son, Hallam:
                <rr-line-indent>
                    on Saturday he [Tennyson] walked home from the Lewes[’] + Part [<i>sic</i>] of the way with them. I called there + stayed some time + then left him + he read some of Maud[.] Mrs Lewes [George Eliot] said that his reading ought to be taken down in notes recitative-wise but that will not give his magnificent voice with its delicate <rr-footnote>intonations</rr-footnote> <n_f_p> [link to TRC/Letters/307 1 & 2] </n_f_p>
                </rr-line-indent>
                This intriguing citation shows a musically sensitive author responding to Tennyson’s reading as if it approximated the operatic (“recitative”), while Emily attributes a more song-like quality to her husband’s “magnificent voice” because of its “delicate <rr-footnote>intonations”.</rr-footnote>  Mrs Tennyson probably felt strongly about this matter for she had already begun setting Tennyson’s poems to music. Of these, “The Song of the Alma River” had been published in 1864 with words and notes attributed to Emily, although Alfred had in fact supplied the first <rr-footnote>stanza.</rr-footnote>  Emily’s correspondent (son, Hallam) would have known about “The Song of the Alma River” and that his mother had been musically treating his father’s poems for years. If Emily had already chosen song as the best way to render her husband’s recitations, how must the Tennysons have felt at Eliot’s idea of recording the reading “recitative-wise”? The two women agree on the musicality, but differ on the level of lyricism.
            </p>

            <p>
                Second, situating Janotha’s contributions within the full list of Emily’s publications shows them to be part of a larger process. Emily’s music was printed either with the original accompaniment or with an arrangement provided by prominent musicians and composers. The former comprise:
                <rr-list-indent>
                    <rr-list-num>
                        “The Song of the Alma River”, music and words Emily Tennyson, both in E major and G major (London: Cramer [1864]).
                    </rr-list-num>
                    <rr-list-num>
                        “Two Child-songs,” music Emily Tennyson, words Alfred Tennyson (London: Novello, [1880]).
                    </rr-list-num>
               </rr-list-indent>
               The arrangements begin to appear more regularly in the 1880s and 1890s. In 1882, Irish composer Charles Villiers Stanford arranged and edited Emily’s setting of “Hands all round,” words by Tennyson, in the keys of E and F (London: Boosey, 1882). This song was also arranged for military band by Kappey (London: Boosey, 1882).  Three years later, Frederick Bridge (organist for Westminster Abbey) arranged “The Gordon Boys’ Morning & Evening Hymns,” words edited by Tennyson and music by Emily (London: Boosey, [1885]). Most numerous of all are Janotha’s arrangements of Emily’s settings of Tennyson’s poems. These published piano/vocal scores are:
               <rr-list-indent>
                    <rr-list-num><i>Songs by Lord Tennyson</i> (London: Chapell [1892]):</rr-list-num>
                    <rr-list-letters>
                        <rr-list-letter>“Look Through Mine Eyes”</rr-list-letter>
                        <rr-list-letter>“In Love, If Love, Be Love”
                        <rr-list-letter>“To Sleep, To Sleep”
                        <rr-list-letter>“Home they brought him”
                        <rr-list-letter>“Lady Let the Rolling Drums”
                        <rr-list-letter>“Airy Fairy Lilian”
                        <rr-list-letter>“Riflemen Form!”
                    </rr-list-letters>
                    <rr-list-num>(2) “Sweet and Low,” <i>The Girl’s Own Paper</i> (1895): 356–8.
                    <rr-list-num>(3) “Break, break, break,” <i>Sunday Hours 2</i> (1897): 568–72.
               </rr-list-indent>
               For Tennyson’s funeral in Westminster Abbey on 12 October 1892, Bridge arranged Emily’s setting of “The Two Voices” for four voices (SATB) and organ (London: Novello, 1892). Long after Emily’s death in 1896, Bridge also arranged her melody for “A Call to Arms” for solo, chorus and symphony (London: Novello, [1914]). The last appeared three or four months after World War I began, available in both traditional staff notation and Tonic Sol-fa (moveable <i>doh</i>), probably because many Victorian and Edwardian choristers only read Tonic <rr-footnote>Sol-fa.</rr-footnote>
            </p>

            <p>
                Of Emily’s three arrangers, Janotha was the most dedicated to promoting and publishing the melodies. Although the accompaniments became more ornate under Janotha’s hand, her arrangements mostly remain true to the vocal line (the part that clearly aligned with the words). When Janotha deviated too far, Emily protested. In one case, Janotha emotionally responded:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/janotha_to_emily_1.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>
                        Figure 1. Janotha to Emily Tennyson, 15 May 1892, TRC/Letters/6873. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote> <n_t_p>[please put this footnote transcription into a link]</n_t_p>
                    </figcaption>
                </figure>
                The extravagant punctuation shows Janotha’s passionate response to the accusation, sandwiched around a more sensible (less punctuated) explanation. We see that Janotha involved English composer Charles Wood in making the arrangements, and that Janotha corrected some of the changes introduced by Wood to Emily’s vocal and piano lines. The result lacked complete fidelity to the original melody. Emily apparently objected. She had made decisions about how to convey Tennyson’s readings (e.g., by composing songs instead of recitatives) and she worked with Janotha, whose choices further influenced that transmission.
            </p>

            <p>
                Yet while Emily endeavored to maintain the original contour of the melodic and rhythmic line, and Janotha strove for beauty, surely the success of the songs’ dissemination partly came down to singability. The difficulties of Emily’s original key choices are highlighted by a more accomplished composer, Stanford, when setting “Hands all Round” for Charles Santley to sing:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/janotha_to_emily_1.jpg" />
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/janotha_to_emily_1.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>
                        Figure 2. Charles Villiers Stanford to Emily Tennyson, 20 February 1882, TRC/Letters/7394. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote> <n_t_p>[please put this footnote transcription into a link]</n_t_p>
                    </figcaption>
                </figure>
                Stanford suspects that a pianist’s instincts (and the look of the staves) guide Emily’s song-setting. Plausibly, the vocal writing also reveals Emily to have been an alto or an untrained singer (most comfortable in chest voice). Regardless, an accomplished baritone could not sing in the low range in which Emily composed – not “with any effect”, at least. Because she maintained the keys of Emily’s settings, we see that Janotha also thought like a pianist, not a singer. Such a perspective materially impacts how effectively the songs could transmit Tennyson’s sonorous choices. As a soprano, I shared baritone Santley’s difficulties. After consulting with musicologist Francesco Izzo, I also decided to transpose Emily’s music up. Not only was performing music in different keys from the original a standard practice in the nineteenth century, but it was also usual to publish music in more than one key, as Stanford mentions in his letter. Because Janotha only published her arrangements in Emily’s original keys, most purchasers would have had themselves to transpose the music if they were to sing it effectively. Because of this effort, the music would be less likely to enter the standard repertoire.
            </p>

            <p>
                Still, Janotha engaged in the usual publicity practices; she promoted the music through performance before it was published. Because of this, we have a sense of how many people heard the music and how it was received. The pianist seems to have introduced the compositions semi-privately for about five hundred students at Balliol College, Oxford on 25 January 1890; at the Stratford Shakespeare fête in March 1891 (a benefit for Shakespeare’s library); in elite salons in 1891; and on the concert stage in March of the same <rr-footnote>year.</rr-footnote>  In salons, a trained performer of the highest caliber presented the songs. Mrs. Edith Lyttelton (née Santley) performed Janotha’s Tennyson arrangements at the home of Liberal MP, Charles Flower in February 1891 and also sang two of them at Mary Drew’s (née Gladstone) private concert on 23 November <rr-footnote>1891.</rr-footnote>  Daughter of Charles Santley, Edith had frequented the concert stage before she married Robert Lyttelton, one of Prime Minister Gladstone’s nephews. Many of the guests at such salon performances would have been able to make a fascinating assessment of this musical repast, for it was just this elite set who would have heard Tennyson recite at other private gatherings.
            </p>

            <p>
                When seven of the piano/vocal pieces were presented on 13 March 1891 at St James’s Hall in London, the audience responded well, even encoring “Airy Fairy Lilian.” <i>The Musical Times</i> appreciated “Airy, fairy Lilian” along with “To Sleep” as showing “a higher standard of merit” than the rest of the <rr-footnote>series.</rr-footnote>  The press noticed with differing levels of approbation or censure Janotha’s heavily ornate, Schumannesque accompaniments to Emily’s melodies, but they also commented on the vocal lines. The reporter from <i>Truth</i> wrote, “Lady Tennyson’s melodies are, for the most part, entirely unconventional, the irregular rhythms apparently being the result of an attempt to fit the words, but the songs are nevertheless an agreeable change from the average drawing room ballad of the period.” Likewise, the <i>Standard</i>: “She avoids formal rhythms and sequential passages, preferring to follow the flow of the words, whether even or <rr-footnote>uneven.”</rr-footnote> 
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/janotha_to_emily_2.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>
                        Figure 3. Natalie Janotha to Emily Tennyson, 15 May 1892, TRC/Letters/6873. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote> <n_t_p>[please put this footnote transcription into a link] </n_t_p>
                    </figcaption>
                </figure>
            </p>

            <p>
                Janotha also kept Emily Tennyson appraised about the pre-publication reception of her songs. (Fig. 3.) Celebrated English soprano Liza Lehmann, who appeared on the same St James’s Hall concert singing Gounod and an English ballad, was impressed enough to ask for the <rr-footnote>songs.</rr-footnote>  Later, interest was shown by acclaimed Canadian soprano Emma Albani who “promised to introduce them at <rr-footnote>Court.”</rr-footnote>  Within high society, too, Janotha reported to Emily the result of the concert: “this public does not forget them, + every – everywhere they mention to me – ‘are the Songs of Lady T. out?’ – at Leeds – ‘ah! your concert was a success – I mean the concert where the Songs were given’ and so <rr-footnote>on!…”.</rr-footnote>  Janotha’s arrangements sold out through pre-orders in October 1892, with a few copies reserved and sent to Queen Victoria, one of the princesses, pianist and composer Clara Schumann, virtuoso violinist Joseph Joachim, the German Empress, baritone Georg Henschel, Liza Lehmann, baritone Harry Plunket Greene (Hubert Parry’s son-in-law), and <rr-footnote>others.</rr-footnote>  The musical and fashionable world thus owned the music, although we might be wise to take Janotha’s enthusiasms with a grain of salt.
            </p>

            <p>
                George Eliot was attuned to preserving the sonorous aspects of the poems, too, but Janotha believed that transmitting Tennyson’s reading voice had national value. Something of Janotha’s motivation may be glimpsed by an astonishing piece of advice that she gave to Emily just twenty days after Tennyson’s death. The pianist wrote to Emily to say that the first edition of <i>Songs by Lord Tennyson</i>, “though not yet out – is already sold out!!!!!!!!!” Janotha continued:
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/janotha_to_emily_3.jpg" />
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <img src="media/janotha_to_emily_4.jpg" />
                </figure>

                <figure>
                    <img src="media/janotha_to_emily_5.jpg" />
                    <figcaption>
                        Figure 4. Janotha to Emily Tennyson, 26 October 1892, TRC/Letters/3814. This item is reproduced by permission of Lincolnshire County Council, <rr-footnote>UK.</rr-footnote> <n_t_p>[please put this footnote transcription into a link]</n_t_p>
                    </figcaption>
                </figure>
                It is Emily’s “sacred duty” to her husband to feed the “<u>heart</u> of the nation” with more of the “precious gems” of his poems, set to Emily’s music. As “musical throats” imbibe (“‘devour’”) the music (perform it), Janotha implies that Tennyson posthumously forms the individual and national body. You are what you eat (or sing), after all. Unsurprisingly, the grieving widow did not immediately fulfill Janotha’s request.
            </p>

            <p>
                Several years later, however, two more songs were made public. Janotha chose from among the fifteen songs sent to her in 1890, of which she had already published seven in 1892. She avoided “Rise Britons Rise,” “Arm, arm, arm!”, “Courage Poor Heart of Stone,” “O Lark!”, “The Sea Fairies” and “Dead Mountain <rr-footnote>Flowers”</rr-footnote>  in favor of “Sweet and Low” from <cite>The Princess</cite>. The last was printed in the wildly popular <cite>The Girl’s Own Paper</cite> in 1895. Established by the Religious Tract Society fifteen years before, this magazine quickly reached over 250,000 <rr-footnote>readers.</rr-footnote>   “Break, break, break,” also arranged by Janotha, appeared in the second and last volume of the journal, <cite>Sunday Hours</cite>, and was dedicated to Queen Victoria. Featured thus, the latter setting shows Janotha’s enduring pious nationalism.
            </p>

            <p>
                “Break, break, break” was, moreover, an obvious choice in 1897. It was published posthumously to both Tennysons (a year after Emily’s death), and dealt with the loss of a friend “pretended to be gone, but who was always here already with God as He is now also always here”, if we might borrow Janotha’s words to Emily upon Tennyson’s death (see above). The poem conveys a similar sentiment, while yearning for material presence: “But O for the touch of a vanished hand, / And the sound of a voice that is still.” (ll 11-12). Of the enormous popularity of this poem in phonograph demonstrations, Matthew Rubery observes that “Tennyson does not ask for the voice itself, only the sound of a voice. The distinction was not lost on contemporary <rr-footnote>observers.”</rr-footnote>   Impressing the demonstrator’s voice on tinfoil sheets or wax cylinders, however, was less multiform and polyphonic than Emily’s musical “impression” of Tennyson’s readings. Arranged by Janotha, the musically-set elegy now featured three vanished hands and three still voices: Arthur Hallam (the original lost friend in the poem), Alfred Tennyson (the written words in his hand; the musical impression of his reciting voice), and Emily Tennyson (written notes and pianistic touch; her singing voice).
            </p>

            <p>
                Unfortunately, due to the demise of the <i>Sunday Hours</i>, this disseminated meaning must have reached a limited audience. In more recent years, too, it has languished; the British Library owns the only extant copy of the short-lived magazine while the Lincolnshire County Council maintains a photocopy of the relevant pages from the <i>Sunday Hours</i>. With the Sounding Tennyson website, the musical setting of “Break, break, break” can be widely disseminated for the first time. With time, we will also add Emily Tennyson’s other musical settings, some of which reached thousands of people at the turn of the century.
            </p>

            <rr-bib>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Hallam</rr-footnote> Tennyson, note, in Emily Tennyson, manuscript music album, TRC/Music/5321, f 1. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Emily</rr-footnote> Tennyson to Hallam Tennyson, 29 August 1871, TRC/Letters/307. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>In</rr-footnote> opera, recitative moves the plot with a vocal line that imitates speech-rhythms, supported by a minimal accompaniment. It is sung, but it lies somewhere between speech and song.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Cecil</rr-footnote> Y. Lang and Edgar F. Shannon, Jr., editorial note, <i>The Letters of Alfred Lord Tennyson, Vol II: 1851:1870</i>, eds Cecil Y. Lang and Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. (Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 1987) 2: 374 n1.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>“Music</rr-footnote> Published during the Last Month: Secular,” <i> New Music Review and Church Music Review</i>, 14. 158 (January 1915): 60; “Tonic Sol-fa Publications,” <i>The Musical Times</i> 55 (1 December 1914): 715.</rr-bib-entry>
 
                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>I</rr-footnote> changed melodies!!?? Lady Tennyson changed accompaniment!? Wood changed both - + I changed at last “all in all” leaving all the beautiful + the only true, as you  liked it!! –</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Dear</rr-footnote> Mrs. Tennyson, The song is published in two keys, E + F. The latter also because Santley can’t sing it in so low a key – The lie of the notes is (as I think I told you at the time) too low for the ordinary voice to bring out with any effect at all – that is if you wish the same voice to sing the high notes as well. I am afraid that even in the higher key the song won’t be so effective when sung as it looks upon paper or sounds on the piano; but this we must risk. I left it to Santley (as the best judge of what his own voice can do) to fix the key - + he chose F as I expected. The song will appear in the original key also I hope that you will not mind. […]</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Janotha</rr-footnote> to Emily Tennyson, 2 January 1890, TRC/Letters/3813; 16 March 1891, TRC/Letters/6866. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Janotha</rr-footnote> to Charles Flower, 21 February 1891, OCLC Number 471921271, Folger Library; Natalie Janotha to Mary Gladstone, 5, 18 and 20 September 1891, Add MS 46245, ff 148, 148, 151. The British Library, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>“Mdlle.</rr-footnote> Janotha’s Concert,” <i>The Musical Times</i> (1 April 1891) 217.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Press</rr-footnote> clippings from the <i>Standard</i>, <i>Truth</i> and <i>The Musical Standard</i>, TRC/Catalogue/6877. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Sweet</rr-footnote> precious composer! On the 26th - Miss Breman sings “Look through mine eyes” “in [<i>sic</i>]Love if Love” – Miss Elliot “Airy Fairy Lilian” (2nd arrangement) – Mr. Ley “to [<i>sic</i>] sleep[,] “Home they brought him[,] “Lady let the rolling[,] + Rifleman. They do adore these songs + I also[.] N. –</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Janotha</rr-footnote> to Hallam Tennyson, 26 March 1892, TRC/Letters/6877. Lincolnshire County Council, UK. See also Janotha to Emily Tennyson, 19 Sept? 1892, TRC/Letters/6874; Janotha to Emily Tennyson, 15 May 1892, TRC/Letters/6873. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Janotha</rr-footnote> to Emily Tennyson, 11 December 1891, TRC/Letters/6869. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Janotha</rr-footnote> to Emily Tennyson, 26 October 1892, TRC/Letters/3814; 31 January 1893, TRC/Letters/6875. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry> <rr-footnote>Now</rr-footnote> Angel dear, it is your sacred duty towards the genius pretended to be gone, but who was always here already with God as He is now also always here – to set those precious gems to your music, as many, as you can!!!!----
                    Because all the Songs will be “devoured” by the musical throats, + by the heart of the nation! ---
                    </rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Note</rr-footnote>, Emily Tennyson, manuscript music album, TRC/Music/5321, flyleaf. Lincolnshire County Council, UK.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Terri</rr-footnote> Doughty, Introduction, <i>Selections from The Girl’s Own Paper, 1880-1907</i>, ed. Terri Doughty (Peterborough, Ontario: Broadview, 2004) 7.</rr-bib-entry>

                    <rr-bib-entry><rr-footnote>Matthew</rr-footnote> Rubery, “Thomas Edison’s Poetry Machine,” 19: <i>Interdisciplinary Studies in the Long Nineteenth Century</i> 18 (2014): 1–25 (18). <a href="http://www.19.bbk.ac.uk/articles/10.16995/ntn.678/">http://www.19.bbk.ac.uk/articles/10.16995/ntn.678/</a> </rr-bib-entry>

                </rr-bib>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>